<Document>
  # Economy System

  The economy in OpenEdge 14 revolves around physical coins and a trading system. Money is not abstract — coins exist as real items in the world that can be picked up, dropped, and stolen.

  ## Currency

  Coins are the primary currency. They come in different denominations and can be carried in your pockets or a wallet. Examine a stack of coins to see their total value.

  [bold]Coin Denominations (from lowest to highest value):[/bold]

  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14CopperCoin1" Caption="Copper Coin"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14SilverCoin1" Caption="Silver Coin"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14GoldCoin1" Caption="Gold Coin"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14PlatinumCoin1" Caption="Platinum Coin"/>
  </Box>

  You earn money by:
  - Collecting your [color=#f0c040]job salary[/color] at a payroll platform
  - [color=#f0c040]Selling items[/color] at trading platforms
  - Harvesting and selling crops and resources

  ## Salary

  Every job accumulates a regular salary over time. To collect it, you must visit a [bold]Payroll Platform[/bold] and interact with it — coins are generated there for you to pick up.

  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14SalaryPlatform" Caption="Salary Platform"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14TradingPlatform" Caption="Trading Platform"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14TradingSellingPlatform" Caption="Selling Platform"/>
  </Box>

  Different jobs pay different amounts. Check the Jobs section for details on each role's salary.

  ## Trading Platforms

  Trading platforms allow you to buy and sell items. Prices are calculated once at the start of each round with a random fluctuation and remain fixed for the entire round — they change again next round.

  To sell an item, place it on the selling platform and confirm the transaction. Coins will be given to you automatically.

  To buy, browse the available stock and select what you want. The cost is deducted from your carried coins.

  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14TradingPlatform"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14TradingSellingPlatform"/>
  </Box>

  [bold]Tips:[/bold]
  - Prices vary between rounds — what sold well last round may be worth less now.
  - Rare crafted items often fetch better prices than raw materials.
  - Keep coins in a wallet to stay organized.

  ## Farming and Resources

  Growing crops and harvesting resources is one of the most reliable ways to earn money. Plant seeds, tend your crops, and sell the harvest at trading platforms.

  Plants regrow after each harvest as long as they have energy. Energy is generated by exposure to light — a plant left in the dark will stop growing. There is no hard limit on harvests; a well-maintained plant can be harvested indefinitely.

  ## Related Systems

  - [textlink="Crafting" link="OE14Crafting"] — create high-value items to sell for maximum profit
  - [textlink="Magic" link="OE14Magic"] — master spellcasting to take on harder contracts
  - [textlink="Combat" link="OE14Combat"] — acquire rare drops from defeated enemies

</Document>
