<Document>
  # Skill System

  The Skill System allows characters to specialize in different combat and magic styles. Each skill tree provides unique bonuses and abilities.

  ## Skill Trees

  Skill trees define what abilities a character can learn. Your species determines which trees you have access to. For example, Elves start with the Metamagic tree for magic enhancement.

  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14MetamagicT1" Caption="Metamagic Tier 1"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14MetamagicT2" Caption="Metamagic Tier 2"/>
  </Box>

  ## How to Gain Skill Points

  Skill points are the currency for learning new abilities. There are two types of skill points:

  [bold]Memory Points[/bold] — used by all standard skill trees (Pyrokinetic, Healing, Metamagic, etc.). Currently these cannot be obtained from items and are only granted through special events or progression.

  [bold]Blood Essence[/bold] — used exclusively by the Vampire skill tree. Vampires gain Blood points by:
  - Being selected as a vampire antagonist (start with 2 Blood points)
  - Consuming [bold]Blood Essence[/bold] items
  - Gathering essence from victims

  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14BloodEssence" Caption="Blood Essence"/>
  </Box>

  Different skill trees require different point types. Most trees use Memory, while the Vampire tree uses Blood.

  ## Learning Skills

  Open your character menu (press C) and navigate to the Skills tab. Available skills appear in the tree. Click on a skill to learn it if you have enough points.

  [bold]Requirements:[/bold]
  - Available skill points (Memory for standard trees, Blood for Vampire)
  - Skill must be in an available tree (determined by species)
  - Some skills require prerequisites (previous skills in the tree)

  ## Free Skills (Species Bonus)

  Some species have innate skills that are learned automatically at character creation. These skills are free and do not require skill points.

  [bold]Example:[/bold]
  - Elf: Metamagic T1 and T2 provide +1 Intelligence bonus each
  - These apply automatically when the character spawns

  ## Skill Effects

  Skills can provide various bonuses:
  - [bold]Stat Modifiers:[/bold] +1 to Strength, Vitality, Dexterity, or Intelligence
  - [bold]Special Abilities:[/bold] Unique combat or magic effects

  [bold]Note:[/bold] Stat modifiers from skills contribute to your effective stats and may cause overflow if they push your stat above 10. In such cases, you receive bonus available points instead.

  ## Related Systems

  - [textlink="Character Stats" link="OE14CharacterStats"] — stats affected by skills
  - [textlink="Combat" link="OE14Combat"] — combat skills for damage bonuses
  - [textlink="Magic" link="OE14Magic"] — magic skills enhance spellcasting

</Document>