<Document>
  # Crafting System

  OpenEdge 14 has three different crafting systems, each suited for different types of items.

  ## Workbench Crafting

  The most common crafting method. Approach a crafting workbench and interact with it to see available recipes. Place the required materials nearby, select a recipe, and wait for the crafting to complete.

  Crafting takes time — a progress bar will appear while your character works. Moving away or taking damage may interrupt the process.

  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14Workbench" Caption="Workbench"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14WorkbenchCooking" Caption="Cooking Table"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14WorkbenchSewing" Caption="Sewing Table"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14WorkbenchAnvil" Caption="Anvil"/>
  </Box>

  [bold]Tips:[/bold]
  - Different workbenches unlock different recipes.
  - Some recipes require tools in addition to materials.

  ## Cooking

  Food is prepared using ovens, fires, and cauldrons. Place raw ingredients into the cooking device and apply heat. Items transform when they reach specific temperatures.

  Pay attention to heat levels — food that gets too hot will burn and become inedible. Different foods require different cooking times.

  [bold]Common cooking tools:[/bold]
  - Fireplace: Basic heat source for simple cooking
  - Oven: More controlled heat, suitable for baked goods
  - Cauldron: Large container for soups and stews
  - Bonfire: High heat, good for grilling

  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14Furnace"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14Cauldron"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14FryingPan"/>
  </Box>

  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14CookingPot"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14Lighter"/>
  </Box>

  ## Modular Crafting

  Advanced crafters can customize weapons and armor with modular parts. Each crafted weapon or armor piece can accept multiple modular components that enhance its properties.

  [bold]Available Modular Parts:[/bold]
  - [bold]Stat Crystals:[/bold] Essence shards that add +1 to specific stats (Strength, Vitality, Dexterity, Intelligence)
  - [bold]Weapon Parts:[/bold] Damage blades and speed hilts to increase weapon damage and attack speed
  - [bold]Armor Parts:[/bold] Heavy plates and protective padding to enhance damage reduction
  - [bold]Mobility Parts:[/bold] Light embrace and agile weave to reduce movement penalties
  - [bold]Magical Parts:[/bold] Mana conduits and amplifiers to reduce spell casting costs

  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14ModularCrystalStrength" Caption="STR Crystal"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14ModularBladeDamage" Caption="Damage Blade"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14ModularArmorPlateHeavy" Caption="Heavy Plate"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14ModularManaReduction" Caption="Mana Conduit"/>
  </Box>

  To apply a modular part to a weapon or armor piece, hold the part item and interact with the weapon. A progress bar will appear as the part assembles. Once attached, the item gains the stat bonuses and mechanical benefits of that part.

  You can also disassemble modular items by damaging them — the parts will drop and can be recovered.

  See the [textlink="Smithing" link="OE14Smithing"] section for detailed recipes and assembly instructions.

  ## Related Systems

  - [textlink="Magic" link="OE14Magic"] — craft vessels to store spells and enchantments
  - [textlink="Combat" link="OE14Combat"] — create weapons tailored to your fighting style
  - [textlink="Smithing" link="OE14Smithing"] — specialize as a blacksmith for advanced weapon and armor crafting
  - [textlink="Economy" link="OE14Economy"] — earn coins by selling crafted goods

</Document>
