<Document>
# Character Stats

Your character has four core attributes that influence how effective you are in different situations. Open the character menu with [bold]C[/bold] to see your current stat values.

Stats range from [bold]1 to 10[/bold]. Stat [bold]5[/bold] is the neutral value — no bonus or penalty.

## Strength

[color=#e05050]Strength[/color] determines how hard you hit in physical combat.

Stat 5 = no bonus (1.0x), Stat 10 = [bold]+50% damage[/bold] (1.5x), Stat 1 = [bold]-50% damage[/bold] (0.5x).

The scale is slightly asymmetric: each point above 5 adds +10%, while each point below 5 subtracts 12.5%.

## Vitality

[color=#50e050]Vitality[/color] determines how much damage you can take before going down.

Each point above or below 5 changes your health by [bold]+/-12.5 HP[/bold] (crit threshold).

Stat 5 = 100 HP to crit / 200 to die, Stat 10 = 162 HP / 325 to die, Stat 1 = 50 HP / 100 to die.

## Dexterity

[color=#50e0e0]Dexterity[/color] determines how much stamina damage you can absorb before being [bold]knocked to the ground[/bold].

Stamina damage accumulates from sprinting, taking hits, and other exertion. When it reaches your [bold]knockdown threshold[/bold], you fall and are briefly stunned. It recovers over time.

Each point above or below 5 changes your threshold by [bold]+/-25%[/bold].

Stat 5 = 100, Stat 10 = 225 (very hard to knock down), Stat 1 = 0 (falls instantly).

## Intelligence

[color=#a050e0]Intelligence[/color] determines how much mana you have available for casting spells.

Each point above or below 5 changes mana by [bold]+/-18.75[/bold].

Stat 5 = 100 mana, Stat 10 = [bold]~194 mana[/bold], Stat 1 = [bold]25 mana[/bold] (minimum — barely enough for one spell).

## Stat Summary

| Stat | Neutral (5) | Max (10) | Min (1) |
|---|---|---|---|
| Strength | 1.0x dmg | 1.5x dmg | 0.5x dmg |
| Vitality | 100 HP crit | 162 HP crit | 50 HP crit |
| Dexterity | 100 knockdown | 225 knockdown | 0 (falls instantly) |
| Intelligence | 100 mana | ~194 mana | 25 mana |

## Stats by Race

Each playable race starts with different stat values, reflecting their strengths and weaknesses. Some races have min-max designs, excelling in one stat but struggling in another. Free racial skills provide additional stat bonuses.

### Race Stats Table

| Race | STR | VIT | DEX | INT | Free Skills | Notes |
|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|
| [bold]Human[/bold] ⭐ | 5 | 5 | 5 | 5 | None | Balanced, 5 spendable points |
| [bold]Elf[/bold] | 6 | 6 | 1 | 7⭐ | Metamagic T1/T2 +INT | Master mage, fragile (INT effective 9) |
| [bold]Goblin[/bold] | 6 | 6 | 7⭐ | 1 | Athletic T1/T2 +DEX | Nimble hunter, near-zero mana (DEX effective 9) |
| [bold]Silva[/bold] | 1 | 7⭐ | 5 | 7 | Healing T1/T2 +VIT | Nature healer, weak fighter (VIT effective 9) |
| [bold]Tiefling[/bold] | 7⭐ | 5 | 2 | 6 | Pyrokinetic T1/T2 +STR | Fire wielder, low stamina (STR effective 9) |
| [bold]Carcat[/bold] | 5 | 5 | 7⭐ | 3 | Electromancy T1/T2 +DEX | Feline reflexes, very limited mana (DEX effective 9) |
| [bold]Dwarf[/bold] | 7⭐ | 7⭐ | 2 | 4 | Hydrosophistry T1/T2 +VIT | Tough and strong, very slow (VIT effective 9) |

⭐ = Stat advantage (highest in that category or received free skill bonus)

## Stat Modifiers

In addition to your base stats, temporary [bold]stat modifiers[/bold] can be gained from equipped skills, spells, or items. These modify your effective stats without changing your base values.

Your [bold]effective stat[/bold] is calculated as: [bold]Base Stat + All Modifiers[/bold].

For example, an Elf with INT 8 who equips a Metamagic skill (+2 INT) has an effective INT of 10 (8 + 2).

<Box>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14ModularCrystalStrength" Caption="+1 STR Crystal"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14ModularCrystalVitality" Caption="+1 VIT Crystal"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14ModularCrystalDexterity" Caption="+1 DEX Crystal"/>
  <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14ModularCrystalIntelligence" Caption="+1 INT Crystal"/>
</Box>

### Modifier Overflow Protection

If a modifier would push your effective stat above 10, the system grants you [bold]available stat points[/bold] as compensation instead of wasting the modifier bonus.

Example: Elf INT 8 gains a +3 modifier spell. Instead of capping at 10 wasted, you get: effective INT capped at 10, plus 1 bonus available point (the overflow of 11 - 10 = 1).

## Spending Stat Points

At character creation you receive [bold]3 points[/bold] to distribute freely across any stats. The character creator shows your base race stats, the bonus you are adding, and the final value.

During gameplay, additional points can be earned through progression and spent from the Character menu ([bold]C[/bold]).

### Point Spending Rules

- Stats max out at [bold]10[/bold]
- You [bold]cannot spend a point[/bold] on a stat that is already at [bold]10 (effective value including modifiers)[/bold]
- If you have equipment with stat modifiers that push you to 10 effective, you must remove it before spending more points on that stat
- Points spent increase your base stat by 1

## Related Systems

- [textlink="Combat" link="OE14Combat"] — Strength and Vitality directly affect your combat effectiveness
- [textlink="Magic" link="OE14Magic"] — Intelligence determines how many spells you can cast before running dry

</Document>
