<Document>
  # Combat System

  Combat in OpenEdge 14 is real-time and skill-based. Success depends on your equipment, your character's skill levels, and your positioning.

  ## Basic Combat

  Click on an enemy to attack with your equipped weapon. Each weapon has an attack speed — faster weapons attack more frequently but deal less damage per hit, while slower weapons hit harder but leave you vulnerable between swings.

  Keep an eye on your health bar. Retreat when low on health and use bandages or healing items to recover.

  ## Weapon Types

  [bold]Bladed weapons[/bold] — swords, daggers, and axes. High damage, good range. Some cause bleeding.

  [bold]Blunt weapons[/bold] — clubs, maces, and hammers. Lower damage but can stun enemies and break armor.

  [bold]Polearms[/bold] — spears and halberds. Long reach lets you attack from a safer distance.

  [bold]Ranged weapons[/bold] — bows and thrown items. Attack from range but require ammunition.

  ### Common Melee Weapons

  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14WeaponSwordIron" Caption="Iron Sword"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14WeaponDaggerIron" Caption="Iron Dagger"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14WeaponWarAxeIron" Caption="War Axe"/>
  </Box>

  ### Ranged Weapons

  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14BowCombat" Caption="Combat Bow"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14Arrow" Caption="Arrows"/>
  </Box>

  ### Shields

  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14WeaponShieldWooden" Caption="Wooden Shield"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14WeaponTowerShieldWooden" Caption="Tower Shield"/>
  </Box>

  ### Healing Items

  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14HerbalBandage1" Caption="Herbal Bandage"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14Gauze1" Caption="Gauze"/>
  </Box>

  ## Status Effects

  Many weapons and spells apply status effects on hit:

  [color=#FF4500]Burning[/color] — deals damage over time. Extinguish with water or rolling.

  [color=#00BFFF]Frozen[/color] — slows movement speed significantly. Warm up near a fire to recover faster.

  [color=#7FFF00]Poisoned[/color] — deals damage over time, stacks with multiple applications. Use an antidote to cure.

  [color=#8B0000]Bleeding[/color] — drains health slowly. Apply bandages to stop bleeding.

  ## Character Stats in Combat

  Your character's stats directly affect combat performance. Check your stats by pressing [bold]C[/bold].

  - [color=#e05050]Strength[/color] — each point above 5 adds [bold]+10% physical damage[/bold]. Stat 10 = +50% (1.5x), Stat 1 = -50% (0.5x).
  - [color=#50e050]Vitality[/color] — each point adds [bold]+/-12.5 HP[/bold] to your crit threshold. Stat 10 = 162 HP crit / 325 HP death.
  - [color=#50e0e0]Dexterity[/color] — each point above 5 adds [bold]+25%[/bold] to your stamina knockdown threshold. Low DEX means a single burst staggers you. Stat 10 = 225, Stat 1 = 0 (falls instantly).
  - [color=#a050e0]Intelligence[/color] — each point adds [bold]+/-25 mana[/bold]. Useful when combining spells and melee. Stat 10 = 225 mana.

  Increasing your stats over time makes a significant difference in how long you survive and how hard you hit. See [textlink="Character Stats" link="OE14CharacterStats"] for a full breakdown.

  ## Skill Progression

  As you fight, your combat skills improve automatically. The more you use a weapon type, the better your character becomes with it. Higher skill levels increase damage dealt and reduce damage received.

  Skills are saved between sessions. A veteran character is significantly more effective in combat than a new one.

  [bold]Skill categories:[/bold]
  - Melee: improves damage with all hand-to-hand weapons
  - Defense: reduces incoming damage over time
  - Magic: increases spell effectiveness and reduces mana costs

  ## Tips

  - Fight enemies at your level — taking on too-powerful foes early leads to quick death.
  - Kite enemies by moving while attacking to avoid taking hits.
  - Status effects can turn the tide of a fight — a frozen enemy cannot dodge.
  - Work with other players — grouped combat is far more effective than solo.
  - Always carry bandages and healing items before heading into dangerous areas.

  ## Related Systems

  - [textlink="Magic" link="OE14Magic"] — enhance your combat prowess with spells and magical buffs
  - [textlink="Crafting" link="OE14Crafting"] — forge superior weapons and armor for your adventures
  - [textlink="Economy" link="OE14Economy"] — sell rare enemy drops for profit and buy better equipment
  - [textlink="Character Stats" link="OE14CharacterStats"] — invest in Strength and Vitality to become a more effective fighter

</Document>
