<Document>
  # Welcome to OpenEdge 14

  OpenEdge 14 is a medieval fantasy multiplayer RPG built on the Space Station 14 engine. You share the world with other players in real time — cooperate, trade, fight, and survive together.

  This section covers the core systems. Use the links in the sidebar to read about each one in detail.


  ## First Steps

  When you spawn, you will have a job and a starting location. Take a moment to look around and get your bearings before acting.

  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14MobHuman" Caption="Your Character"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14WeaponSwordIron" Caption="Starting Weapon"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14CopperCoin1" Caption="Starting Coins"/>
  </Box>

  [bold]Open your inventory[/bold] with [bold]I[/bold] — check what items you start with. Different jobs spawn with different equipment.

  [bold]Open your action bar[/bold] with [bold]Q[/bold] — if you are holding a magical item, your spells appear here.

  [bold]Open the character menu[/bold] with [bold]C[/bold] — this shows your character stats: Strength, Vitality, Dexterity, and Intelligence.

  [bold]Right-click[/bold] on objects and characters to see context options: pick up, examine, interact, attack.


  ## Staying Alive

  Your [color=#e05050]health bar[/color] appears at the bottom of the screen. If it reaches zero, you are critically injured and will die without help.

  - Carry [bold]bandages[/bold] to stop bleeding.
  - Eat and drink regularly to maintain stamina.
  - Avoid fighting enemies that are too strong for your current gear.
  - If you are in danger, [bold]run[/bold] — there is no shame in retreating.


  ## Core Systems

  [bold]Magic[/bold] — equip magical staffs to gain spells. Cast them using mana from the action bar.

  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14MagicFireStaff" Caption="Magic Staff"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14SpellScrollFireball" Caption="Spell Scroll"/>
  </Box>

  [bold]Crafting[/bold] — use workbenches to build items, cook food over fires, and assemble custom weapons from components.

  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14Workbench" Caption="Workbench"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14WorkbenchAnvil" Caption="Anvil"/>
  </Box>

  [bold]Economy[/bold] — earn coins from your job salary, sell goods at trading platforms, and grow crops for profit.

  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14GoldCoin1" Caption="Gold Coin"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14TradingPlatform" Caption="Trading Platform"/>
  </Box>

  [bold]Combat[/bold] — fight with melee weapons, apply status effects, and improve your skills with practice.

  <Box>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14WeaponWarAxeIron" Caption="War Axe"/>
    <GuideEntityEmbed Entity="OE14HerbalBandage1" Caption="Herbal Bandage"/>
  </Box>

  [bold]Character Stats[/bold] — your Strength, Vitality, Dexterity, and Intelligence values affect damage, health, stamina, and mana.


  ## Tips for New Players

  - [bold]Read item descriptions[/bold] — examine items to learn what they do before using them.
  - [bold]Talk to other players[/bold] — veterans are usually willing to help newcomers.
  - [bold]Stick to your job role[/bold] early on — your job gives you tools and a salary to get started.
  - [bold]Death is not the end[/bold] — you respawn after a delay. Use the time to think about what went wrong.
  - [bold]Coins are physical[/bold] — keep them in a pouch so you don't drop them when you take damage.

</Document>
